# Yousuf Motiwala Data Scientist

✓ yousuf.s.motiwala@gmail.com

+919029506876

in Yousuf Motiwala

# **Profile Summary**

Data Scientist specialised in Strategy Consulting with 5 Years of experience & a strong academic background. Expertise in driving tangible impact through advanced techniques such as price optimisation, propensity modelling, marketing mix modelling, credit risk modelling, business process automation & NLP. Successfully assisted market leaders across industries such as Consumer-Retail, Telco, IG, Public-Sector & Media to achieve diverse business objectives using advanced analytics.

## **Professional Experience**

#### **Boston Consulting Group**

Senior Analyst 2023 – present Bangalore, India

 Assisted Agriculture Ministry of South Asian country in designing a national-level agricultural land database; the case got presented to Prime Minister's Office

Analyst - Predictive Analytics 2021 - 2022

- Designed customer acquisition strategy for 350M potential user base using customer segmentation and propensity modelling for a leading US health insurance firm
- Devised a Price Optimization Algorithm for a US-based semiconductor manufacturer, leveraging price-elasticity and LR to identify an additional 20% revenue opportunity.
- Added a new BCG capability on non-linear optimisation programming to identify optimal transport frequency based on operational, waiting time & crowding discomfort cost
- Built a Credit Risk ML model that buckets applications based on predicted risk and reduced 30% of the manual screening workload for an India-based NBFC
- Developed M&A strategy by identifying P&Ls & market viewership synergies that generated an additional 7% profit opportunity for India's largest Media & Entertainment merger.
- Developed a predictive ML model to identify profit drivers & set branch strategy to untapped additional 25% profit opportunity for a Vietnamese bank

### Nielsen

Executive - Insights (FMCG & Beverages) 2018 - 2019

- Designed 3 Annual retail sales Brand Plans for India's third-largest beverage firm; won "Simply Excellent award" & generated an additional 5% revenue opportunity
- Mentored three associates, and led a team of five on pack-price-distribution strategy for India's largest snacking brand. Unlocked additional 0.3% growth opportunity

Analyst - Insights (FMCG)

- Identified pack & channel optimisation strategy for a leading Juice brand, resulting in an additional 1.5% share gain opportunity
- Designed case study on "Revamping distribution through Product Innovation" for India's leading FMCG firm. Achieved "Exceeds Expectations" for the analyses

#### **Education**

## **Bayes Business School (Triple Crown Accreditation)**

MSc Business Analytics - Specialized in Applied ML - Distinction

2019 - 2020 London, UK

#### **Vodafone UK:**

Data Scientist - MSc Dissertation - 6 months

 Developed a Ranking Methodology to prioritize locations for 5G investment using Geo-Clustering ML algorithm

Mumbai, India

Bangalore, India

2017 - 2018 Mumbai, India

Bachelor of Management Studies

CGPA: 6.4/7.0 (Top 10%)

#### **Skills**

- **Skills:** Predictive Machine Learning, Geo-analytics, Linear & Non-Linear Optimisation, Credit Risk Modelling, Market-Mix modelling, Time-series forecasting & NLP
- Tools: Python, R, SQL, Alteryx, Tableau, Power BI, Advance MS Excel (VBA), GCP, PySpark

## **Awards & Certifications**

- BCG: Olympics 2021 best cases Finalist (NAMR) For the Lighthouse project
- Nielsen: Simply Excellent Silver for delivering actionable insights to the client's sales team
- Nielsen: Simply Excellent Bronze for exemplifying client-centricity
- NIIT 3 Yrs Diploma certificate in Data Science (CGPA: 9.0/10.0)

#### Langauges

Fluent in English, Gujarati, Urdu and Hindi; Intermediate in Arabic